Indiana Religious Studies Project records, 1976-1997 C298
Indiana University Archives
Indiana Religious Studies Project records
1976-1997
1978-1985
Indiana University Archives
Indiana Religious Studies Project
C298
2.4 cubic feet
Formed in 1977, the Indiana Religious Studies Project (IRSP) brought Indiana secondary teachers to Indiana University to improve how the study of religion was taught in high schools. The collection consists of participant information (applications, course projects, correspondence), sample lesson plans, and a variety of records that pertain to the growth, successes, and shortcomings of the project over its seven year existence. The project's funding ended in 1984.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Advance notice is required.
Administrative History
Established in 1977 in response to the Supreme Court decision (Abington School District v. Schempp & Murray v. Curlett, 1963) that prohibited the practice of religion in public schools though encouraged the continual teaching about religion, the Indiana Religious Studies Project sought to improve how religion was presented to high school students. The goal of the program was to further educate and train secondary teachers so they would have a better knowledge of religious studies and possess other resources, such as lesson plans and curriculum ideas, to use when teaching their students about various religions.
Each year, the Project brought together approximately 18 secondary school teachers from Indiana public schools to Indiana University for a six-week training seminar (following the 1979 program, the project was shortened to three- and four-weeks). During these sessions, the teachers attended classes and lectures taught by faculty from the Department of Religious Studies at Indiana University and Wabash College. The participants also prepared presentations and lesson plans that focused on a variety of areas of study such as world religions, religious theory, and religious texts.
The Project gained funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities and the Lilly Foundation and flourished for nearly seven years. In 1984, the Project lost funding, and it officially ended in July of that year, though it would publish its newsletter until 1985.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into five series: Newsletters; Participants; Subject files; Sample lesson plans; and Cassette tapes.
Scope and Content Note
The Indiana Religious Studies Project records date between 1976 and 1997 with the bulk of the records dating between 1978 and 1985. The records are organized into five series: Newsletters; Participants; Sample lesson plans; Subject files; and Cassette tapes.
The Newsletter series contains the newsletters that were published from Spring 1981 to Spring 1985. In all cases except 1985 (when the project ended), the newsletter was published biannually – once in the Spring and once in the Fall. Each newsletter contains general information about the project, the current expectations and goals of the project, and discusses several current resources for teachers of religious studies. The newsletters are approximately four pages in length and have been arranged chronologically.
The Participants series, 1977-1981, contains applications, course projects, evaluations, and some pre- and post-project correspondence between the organizers of the program and the participant. It appears that the participants produced the course projects as part of their course workload. While the projects vary in length, most projects are lesson plans designed for classroom use and contain assignments, lecture information, handouts, exams, and photocopies of secondary texts (used to verify the information and/or serve as student readings). The evaluations that, in most cases, follow the course projects were written by ISRP instructors and provide commentary and positive and negative feedback regarding the participant's work. The series has been arranged alphabetically by the participant's surname, and files include application and pre-project correspondence, participant's course projects, evaluations, and post-project correspondence. In the application materials, social security numbers have been blacked out by the processor.
The Sample lesson plans, 1978-1985, appear to be revised versions of selected participant's original projects. In similar format to the participant's projects, the sample lesson plans contain classroom assignments, lecture information, handouts, exams, and photocopies of secondary texts. The original sample lesson plans are in layout form with articles, assignments, handouts, etc. having been cut apart and taped to pages in preparation for photocopying. In several instances, the photocopied version accompanies the original sample lesson plan. Folders in this series have been arranged per the original order; consequently for some years some participants have their own folders, while for other years no distinction is made between participants. The folders in this series have been arranged alphabetically, and materials within the folders are arranged chronologically.
The Subject files series, 1976-1997, contains a wide variety of information about the project, its origins, and its yearly activities. Of particular interest to understanding the development of the ISRP may be the cover letter and description (undated), along with the final reports (1978, 1985), and the grant proposals (1978, undated), that provide detailed descriptions about the purpose and progress of the project. These reports and descriptions were written by the acting director of the ISRP. Several files provide lists of participants and their contact information (participant data, participant lists, description and participant profile), while other files offer general information about the class schedules and course work of the secondary teachers during the project (curriculum unites, schedule of classes, and syllabus by track). Although the ISRP ended in 1985, the Indiana University's religious department continued to receive requests for sample lesson plans; these letters account for the majority of the general correspondence following 1985. The Subject files series have been arranged alphabetically by subject and chronologically within the folders.
It is unclear if the cassette tapes, 1978-1980, resulted from lectures by instructors during the project or were recorded elsewhere and used as teaching aids by the ISRP. The labels on each cassette have been recorded on the finding aid. The cassettes were in no discernable original order and are currently in no established order in box 4, though they are listed chronologically.
Separated Material
Records containing social security numbers have been removed and shredded. Duplicate records have been removed and discarded.
Acquisition Information
Accession 2003/006
Provenance
Transferred from the Department of Religious Studies to the University Archives on 21 January 2003.
Appraisal
Duplicate records have been removed. A newspaper clipping has been photocopied and the original article discarded. Records containing social security numbers have been removed.
Religion in the public schools --Indiana.; Teaching --Indiana --Religious aspects.; Education --Curricula --Indiana --History --20th century --Sources.; Education --Curricula --Religious aspects.; Indiana Religious Studies Project -- Archives; Indiana Religious Studies Project -- Records and correspondence; Indiana Religious Studies Project -- History -- Sources
- Newsletters, 1981-1985
  - Spring, Fall (Box 1)
    - 1981 (Box 1)
    - 1982 (Box 1)
    - 1983 (Box 1)
  - General, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Spring, Fall, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Spring, 1985 (Box 1)
- Participants, 1977-1981
  - Ackerman, Ann (Loogoote H.S.) (Box 1)
    - 1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1981, undated (Box 1)
  - Armstrong, Rev. Daniel F. (Bishop Chatard H.S.), 1978 (Box 1)
  - Ayers, Sister Margaret R. (Marian Heights Academy), 1979; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Burks, Kathryn W. (Broad Ripple H.S.), 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - Clemens, Daniel C. (Lewis Cass Jr.-Sr. H.S.), 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Dubiel, Richard M. (Central Catholic H.S.), 1979; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Fisher, Kenneth D. (Bedford-N. Lawrence H.S.), 1978 (Box 1)
  - Gibboney, Colleen J. (Huntington North H.S.), 1979 (Box 1)
  - Grebe, Judy M. (Mount Vernon Senior H.S.), 1979-1981 (Box 1)
  - Hammer, Toni A. (Emmerich Manual H.S.), 1978 (Box 1)
  - Hanlin, Donald A. (Center Grove H.S.), 1978 (Box 1)
  - Hasler, Gloria J. (North Central H.S.), 1978 (Box 1)
  - Headings, Lois (South Side H.S.) (Box 1)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - 1979, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Hefley, Beverly (Elkhart Central H.S.), 1979; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Hendricks, Ellen L. (Forest Park H.S.) (Box 1)
    - 1977-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Horrigan, Kevin (Bishop Chatard H.S.), 1978; 1980 (Box 1)
  - Hudson, Sue C. (Van Buren H.S.), 1978 (Box 1)
  - Hutton, Gary W. (Floyd Central H.S.) (Box 1)
    - 1978 (Box 1)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Ingleman, Beth (Ben Davis H.S.), 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Jones, Inez W. (Jeffersonville H.S.), 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Martin, Dawn (Elkhart Central H.S.), 1979 (Box 1)
  - May, John S. (L & M H.S.), 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - McClure, Fancile C. (North Central H.S.), 1978 (Box 1)
  - McCord, Clinton E. (Seymour H.S.), 1978-1979; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - McLaren, Eleanore S. (Lawrence North H.S.), 1979-1981 (Box 1)
  - Messenger, Lyle A. (Danville H.S.), 1979 (Box 1)
  - Oesch, Oliver S. (West Lafayette Senior H.S.), 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Power, Nita L. (Tri-West H.S.), 1978 (Box 2)
  - Reichel, Ronald (Crispus Attucks H.S.), 1979 (Box 2)
  - Sam, Gloria (Broad Ripple H.S.), 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Toothman, Susan (West Washington Community School), 1978-1980 (Box 2)
  - Vierling, Cheryl (Crothersville, H.S.), 1979 (Box 2)
- Sample lesson plans, 1978-1985
  - Fall, Winter, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Originals (Box 2)
    - 1978 (Box 2)
    - 1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980 (Box 2)
    - 1981 (Box 2)
    - 1982 (Box 2)
    - 1983 (Box 2)
  - Notes, 1983-1984 (Box 2)
  - Preus, J. Samuel (Box 2)
    - Fall, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Spring, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Requests for Lesson Plans, 1985; undated (Box 2)
  - Stein, Stephen J. (Box 2)
    - Fall, 1984 (Box 2)
    - 1984 (Box 2)
    - Fall, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Strawn, Virginia (Box 2)
    - Fall, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Spring, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Wilson, Patricia, Spring, 1985 (Box 2)
- Subject files, 1976-1997
  - Alumni Day (Box 2)
    - 1982 (Box 2)
    - 1983 (Box 2)
  - Announcements, 1979-1982 (Box 2)
  - Audio-Visual Center, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
  - Cartoon, undated (Box 2)
  - Cover Letter & Project Description, undated (Box 2)
  - Curriculum Units, 1978-1982 (Box 2)
  - Description and Participant Profile, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Evaluation Results, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Exams, 1980-1983 (Box 2)
  - Field Report on Curriculum Units (blank), undated (Box 2)
  - File Indexes, 1978-1980 (Box 2)
  - Final Reports, 1982; 1985 (Box 2)
  - General Correspondence, 1987-1990; 1997 (Box 2)
  - Grant Proposals, 1978; undated (Box 2)
  - Indiana Humanities Project, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Information for Participants, 1980; 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - Interim Reports, 1981; 1983 (Box 2)
  - Letters to Alumni, 1980; undated (Box 2)
  - Letters to Participants, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Maxi Duplicating Work Requests, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
  - Participant Data (Box 2)
    - 1978 (Box 2)
    - 1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980 (Box 2)
    - 1981 (Box 2)
    - 1982 (Box 2)
    - 1983 (Box 2)
  - Poster, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Project Awards, 1980-1983 (Box 2)
  - Project Survey, 1984; undated (Box 2)
  - Schedule of Classes (Box 2)
    - 1978 (Box 2)
    - 1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980 (Box 2)
    - 1981 (Box 2)
    - 1982 (Box 2)
    - 1983 (Box 2)
  - Staff Meetings, 1978-1982; undated (Box 2)
  - Statements of Account, 1984-1985; 1987 (Box 2)
  - Syllabus by Track (Box 2)
    - 1980 (Box 2)
    - 1982 (Box 2)
    - 1983 (Box 2)
- Cassette tapes, 1978-1981
  - One Cassette: (Box 3)
    - Side 1: Savrey/Ackerman, N.T. Texts, Bible Seminar, October 21-23, 1979 (Box 3)
      Online Streaming in Media Collections Online
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/w9505h107
    - Side 2: Ackerman, N.T. Texts, Bible Seminar, October 21-23, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Three Cassettes: Ethical Issues in Biblical Narrative (Box 3)
    - Cassette 1: (Box 3)
      - Side 1: Savren, Vindication of Jacob, October 30, 1978 (Box 3)
      - Side 2: Sampley, Jesus and the Family, Bible Seminar, October 30, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Cassette 2: Ackerman, Sampley, Savren, Bible Seminar, Jonah, October 30, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Cassette 3: Ackerman, Sampley, Savren, Bible Seminar, October 31, 1978 (Box 3)
  - One Cassette: (Box 3)
    - Side 1: Alvin Rosenfeld, Jewish-Christian Relations, November 12, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Side 2: David Owen (Box 3)
  - One Cassette: Choula Prious, Jewish-Christian Relations, November 13, 1978 (Box 3)
    https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/w0892t73s
  - One Cassette: (Box 3)
    - Side 1: M. Morgan, Jewish-Christian Relations, Holocaust, November 14, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Side 2: A.E. Cory, Jewish-Christian Relations, November 14, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Two Cassettes: Religion and Mental Health (Box 3)
    - Cassette 1: (Box 3)
      - Side 1: Smith, Ethics in Psychotherapy, May 8, 1979 (Box 3)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/3t946772z
      - Side 2: Smith, Ethical Issues and Psychotherapy, May 8, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Cassette 2: (Box 3)
      - Side 1: M.J. Weaver, Sabbath and Alienation, May 6, 1979 (Box 3)
      - Side 2: No Label (Box 3)
  - One Cassette: Dr. Anne Doherty, Religion and Mental Health, Religion and Psychology, May 7, 1979 (Box 3)
    https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/cn69mm35g
  - One Cassette: C. Finn and P. Olliville, Religion and Mental Health, Well-Being and Religious Contemplation, May 7, 1979 (Box 3)
    https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/vt151188t
  - One Cassette: (Box 3)
    - Side 1: Paula Hadis, Religion and the Family, May 20-22, 1979 (Box 3)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/xw42nr90d
    - Side 2: No Label (Box 3)
  - One Cassette: Peggy Steinfels, Religion and Family, Teenage Pregnancy, May 20-22, 1979 (Box 3)
    https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/dv140996g
  - One Cassette: Finey Weaver, Religion and Family: Traditional Family and Singleness, May 20-22, 1979 (Box 3)
    https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/d217r662n
  - One Cassette: Bible Seminar, J. Ackerman, Job, October 21-23, 1979 (Box 3)
    https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/n009wj761
  - One Cassette: (Box 3)
    - Side 1: Ackerman/Savren, Bible Seminar, Pavidin[?] Covenant / Jeremiah, October 21-23, 1979 (Box 3)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/kw52js00p
    - Side 2: Ackerman/Savren, Bible Seminar, Covenant / Jeremiah, October 21-23, 1979 (Box 3)
  - One Cassette: (Box 3)
    - Side 1: Ackerman/Savren, Wisdom Literature, Dohelet [?], Bible Seminar, October 1979 (Box 3)
    - Side 2: Ackerman/Savren, Dohelet [?], Bible Seminar, October 1979 (Box 3)
  - One Cassette: (Box 3)
    - Side 1: Jim Ackerman, Jewish-Christian Relations (Box 3)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/7h14b723d
    - Side 2: Nancy Fachs-Kreimer, Jewish-Christian Relations, November 13, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Two Cassettes: Ann Ackbar Lecture Cassettes (Box 3)
    General
    (from folder: C298, Participants, Ackerman, Ann, 1979 )
    - Cassette 1: Stein, Mormons (Box 3)
    - Cassette 2: Steve Stein Lecture, Black Nation of Islam (Box 3)
  - Two Cassettes: (Box 3)
    - Joan Huber, Dilema of Feminism, May 18-20, 1980 (Box 3)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/1c18f030z
  - One Cassette: Husten Smith, Abrahamic Religions, Danneri Jerusalem, November 15, 1981 (Box 3)
    https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/h989rm35t
  - One Cassette: Goldenberg (Box 3)
  - One Cassette: Liebes (Box 3)
  - One Cassette: (Box 3)
    - Side 1: Mendes-Flohr (Box 3)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/j6731m638
    - Side 2: No Label (Box 3)